Guide to the Sybil Pittman Estess Collection
University of Houston Libraries
Sybil Pittman Estess Collection
1966-2014
2000-2008
03/2014-031
Estess, Sybil P., 1942-
1.50 linear feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
This collection includes anthologies and journals that contain Estess’ poetry and reviews. Whole volumes are arranged alphabetically by journal title.
Biographical Information:
A native of Mississippi, Sybil Pittman Estess received her Ph.D. from Syracuse University. In the years that followed, her writing career resulted in five collections of poems, a biography of Elizabeth Bishop, a creative writing textbook, and numerous additional poems in edited volumes. Dr. Estess taught classes at the University of Houston, the University of St. Thomas, Rice University, Houston Community College, Blinn Colleges, as well as for Inprint and the C. G. Jung Center. She was nominated for Poet Laureate of the State of Texas in 2015.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
University of Houston -- Faculty
Genre/Form of Material:
poetry; serials (publications)
Personal Name:
Bishop, Elizabeth
Topical Term:
American poetry; Women poets
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes anthologies and journals that contain Estess’ poetry and reviews. Whole volumes are arranged alphabetically by journal title. In addition, the collection includes copies and tear sheets of various other poems and writings by the author. These are arranged alphabetically according to the title of the work or the title of the original publication. Estess’ original folder labels and organization have been retained.
Detailed List of Contents
- Published Writings in Journals
  - “Girl on a Swing”, in Anima: An Experimental Journal, Spring 1985 (Box 1, Item 1)
  - “Sketches”, in Aura, Spring 1976 (Box 1, Item 2)
  - “Returning: High Place on a Lake”, in Concho River Review, Fall 2012 (Box 1, Item 3)
  - “Students Reading Together on Her Bed”, in Concho River Review, Fall 2001 (Box 1, Item 4)
  - “On the Traditions of Contemporary Poetry”, in Denver Quarterly, Summer 1978 (Box 1, Item 5)
  - “Shells”, in Descant, 2007 (Box 1, Item 6)
  - “Laundry on the Veranda”, in Descant, 2008 (Box 1, Item 7)
  - “Edge (Esalen, Big Sur, CA)”, in Descant, 2012 (Box 1, Item 8)
  - “Pegasus Winding”, in Embers: A Collection by Artists and Writers, 1984 (Box 1, Item 9)
  - “Directions” in Forum: A Journal of the Humanities and Fine Arts, 1984 (Box 1, Item 10)
  - “Mastodon Teeth” in Houston Poetry Fest Anthology, 1985 (Box 1, Item 11)
  - “September Shrimp Fleet at Dawn”, in i.e. Magazine, Undated (Box 1, Item 12)
  - “Review: On Five Poets”, in The Iowa Review, Fall 1980 (Box 1, Item 13)
  - “Past Halfway: The Retrieval System, by Maxine Kumin”, in The Iowa Review, Fall 1979 (Box 1, Item 14)
  - “Review: Bear Crossings: An Anthology of North American Poets. Eds Anne Newman and Julie Suk. Newport Beach CA: New South Company 1978.”, in Journal of the American Academy of Religion, June 1981 (Box 1, Item 15)
  - “Review: Women, Literature, Criticism (Bucknell Review). Edited by Harry R. Garvin. Lewisburg, PA: Bucknell University Press, and London: Associated University Presses, 1978.”, in Journal of the American Academy of Religion, September, 1981 (Box 1, Item 16)
  - “Sybil Pittman Estess”, in Langdon Review of the Arts in Texas, 2006-2007 (Box 1, Item 17)
  - “Review: Where Skulls Speak Wind: Poems by Larry D. Thomas. Texas Review Press, 2004.”, in Louisiana Literature: A Review of Literature and the Humanities, Spring/Summer, 2005 (Box 1, Item 18)
  - “Across Waves” & “I Have a Pair of Earrings”, in Louisiana Literature: A Review of Literature and the Humanities, 2010 (Box 1, Item 19)
  - “Flight”, in Manhattan Poetry Review 6“Flight”, in Manhattan Poetry Review 6, Winter/Spring, 1985/86 (Box 1, Item 20)
  - “God’s Rainbow of Hope”, in The Beginning of the Rainbow: The Story of Noah’s Ark, Christ Church Cathedral, May Fete 1987 (Box 1, Item 21)
  - “The Rattlesnake Dream”, in The Midwest Quarterly: A Journal of Contemporary Thought, Summer 1999 (Box 1, Item 22)
  - “The Anointment”, in Mississippi Review, Spring 2004 (Box 1, Item 23)
  - “Coffee in Cazenovia”, in New Texas 91 Poetry and Fiction, 1991 (Box 2, Item 1)
  - “Café Hacienda in Houston”, in New Texas ’99, 1999 (Box 2, Item 2)
  - “The Country Idiot”, in Mississippi Writers: Reflections of Childhood and Youth Vol III: Poetry, 1988 (Box 2, Item 3)
  - “Review: Shelters for ‘What is Whithin’: Meditation and Epiphany in the Poetry of Elizabeth Bishop” in Modern Poetry Studies, Spring 1977 (Box 2, Item 4)
  - “Esther Decides” in The Paris Review, Spring 1994 (Box 2, Item 5)
  - “One thing it Was” and “Blowing Sand May Exist”, in The Paris Review, Summer 1998 (Box 2, Item 6)
  - “The Crisis Angel”, in Rattle: Poetry for the 21st Century, Summer 2004 (Box 2, Item 7)
  - “A Half-Century of descant’s Counter Melodies”, in Texas Books in Review, Fall/Winter 2008/2009 (Box 2, Item 8)
  - “Sunset on the Bayou: For the Challenger Seven”, in Texas in Poetry 2, 2002 (Box 2, Item 9)
  - “Sarah’s Mule”, in The Texas Review, Spring/Summer, 2000 (Box 3, Item 1)
  - “Out of Africa”, in The Texas Review, Fall/ Winter, 2002 (Box 3, Item 2)
  - “Review: Amazing Grace. Larry D. Thomas. Texas Review Press, 2001.”, in The Texas Review, Spring/Summer 2002 (Box 3, Item 3)
  - “Review: Blue Alleys: Prose Poetry. Paul Christensen. Stone River Press, 2001.”, in The Texas Review, Spring /Summer 2003 (Box 3, Item 4)
  - “The Wide Net”, in The Texas Review, Spring/Summer 2004 (Box 3, Item 5)
  - “Native on Land”, in Western Humanities Review, Spring 1992 (Box 3, Item 6)
  - “E-Mail by Love”, in Western Humanities Review, Spring 1996 (Box 3, Item 7)
  - “Site of a Pishkun”, in The Willamette Journal of the Liberal Arts, Spring 1984 (Box 3, Item 8)
  - “In Houston I Go to the P.O.”, in Whiskey Island Magazine, 1999 (Box 3, Item 9)
  - “Sight of a Luminous Pear Tree in Houston” in “The Icon Room at the Villa de Matel”, in Windhover: A Journal of Christian Literature, 1999 (Box 3, Item 10)
  - “Ash Wednesday and the Houston Anglican Priest”, in Windhover: A Journal of Christian Literature, January 2006 (Box 3, Item 11)
  - “Toward the Interior: Epiphany in ‘Cape Breton’ As Representative Poem”, in World Literature Today, Winter, 1977 (Box 3, Item 12)
- Tear Sheets and Copies
  - “Symmetric Again”, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - “Review: The Search for Home: Elizabeth Bishop, Life and the Memory of It. Brett C. Miller. University of California Press.”, in America, February, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - “Interview with Denise Levertov”, in American Poetry Observed: Poets on Their Work, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - “Snow Ice Cream”, in Journal of Texas Women Writers, Spring 2009 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - “Stained Glass”, in Cedar Rock, Winter, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - “On the Traditions of Contemporary Poetry”, in Contemporary Poetry, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - “Holiday Letters from Home”, in Gulf Stream, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - “Review: One Way to Reconstruct the Scene. By William Virgil Davis. The Collected Poems of Sterling A. Brown. By Sterling A. Brown. Any Body’s Song. By Joseph Langland. Denizens. By Ronald Perry. Folly River. By Wendy Salinger. Silks. By Roberta Spear.”, in Iowa Review, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - “Review: Women, Culture, and Society. Edited by Michelle Zimbalist Rosaldo and Louise Lampshere. Stanford: Stanford University Press, 1975.”, in Journal of the American Academy of Religion, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - “Christmas in the Hardware Store”, in Journal of Texas Women Writers, Spring 2009 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - “Wishes and Needs”, in Manhattan Review or Embers (unknown), undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - “Nature, Culture, and the Location of Women in the Poetry of Mary Barnard”, Tearpage, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - “The Woman Who Married Her Brother-In-Law”, in The New Republic, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - “Pretending You Were Joseph”, in The New Republic, May, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - “Elizabeth Bishop and Her Art”, in The New York Times Book Review, February 27, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - “Past Halfway: The Retrieval System, By Maxine Kumin” (unknown), undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - “Review: My Brother George Seferis. By Ioanna Tsatsos” in Southern Humanities Review, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - “Elizabeth Bishop: The Delicate Art of Map Making” in The Southern Review, Autumn, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - “Review: The Eden of Edisto: The Fall into the ‘Then-Next’ By Padgett Powell” in Southwest Review, Autumn, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - “Symmetric Again” in Studia Mystica, Summer 1983 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - “Say a Little Prayer” in The Texas Observer, September, 2008 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - “Sea Dreams”, in Passages North, Spring/Summer, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 22)